Guide to the Backhouse and Mounsey Collection
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
Backhouse and Mounsey collection
1819-1856
MSS 13
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
2
2 volumes + 1 box
The collection comprises etchings, lithographs, and drawings by Edward Backhouse, Edward Backhouse Mounsey, and other members of the Backhouse and Mounsey families of Darlington (County Durham) in the early 19th century.
Backhouse, Edward, 1808-1879
Backhouse, Rachel, 1826-1898
Mounsey, Edward Backhouse, 1840-1911
Mounsey, Thomas, 1793-1850
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series: I. Albums; II. Etchings and drawing book by Edward Backhouse Mounsey; III. Copper plates by Thomas Mounsey.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises etchings, lithographs, and drawings by Edward Backhouse, Edward Backhouse Mounsey, and other members of the Backhouse and Mounsey families of Darlington (County Durham) in the early 19th century. The collection demonstrates that a number of family members practiced etching as a hobby. They were also early adopters of lithography, although the quality of the lithographic work is frequently less refined.
Some of Edward Backhouse's etchings present in the current collection appear to have been self-published in the 1840s.
Related Material
Pease Family Collection of Sketchbooks and Exercise Books (MSS 6). Yale Center for British Art, Department of Rare Books and Manuscripts. (http://hdl.handle.net/10079/fa/ycba.mss.0006)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired 2009, Paul Mellon Fund.
Biographical / Historical
The Backhouse family of Darlington, County Durham, were prominent 18th- and 19th-century naturalists and horticulturists. The Backhouses were also Quakers and important bankers. They aligned themselves with the Pease family--also Quakers of Darlington--to become prominent 19th-century industrial financiers (becoming the principal underwriters of the Stockton and Darlington Railway in the 1820s).
Edward Backhouse (1808-1879) was a Quaker minister and historical writer. He was born in Darlington on 8 May 1808, but lived for most of his life in Sunderland, where he was a partner--but not an active one--in the family colliery and banking businesses. He was a member of the Society of Friends and devoted himself to philanthropic and religious causes. In 1856 he married Katharine, daughter of Thomas and Mary Mounsey of Sunderland; they had no children. He wrote several religious histories, including Biographical memoirs: being a record of the Christian lives, experiences, and deaths of members of the religious Society of Friends from its rise to 1653 (published 1854), and Early Church History to the Death of Constantine (published, posthumously, in 1884) which offers a Quaker perspective of the early church.
A good amateur painter, he was also interested in natural history, and illustrated several works written by his second cousin James Backhouse, including: Narrative of a visit to the Australian Colonies (1843) and Narrative of a visit to the Mauritius and South Africa (1844). In the 1840s, he self-published collections of his own etchings of birds.
Edward Backhouse Mounsey (1840-1911) of Darlington, was the nephew of Edward Backhouse and son of John and Lucy Backhouse Mounsey. In 1878, he married Rachel Ann Fryer. He was a member of the Society of Friends and played an important role in the family banking business.
Thomas Mounsey (1793-1850) was the son of Ann Robson and John Mounsey. He married Mary Capper (ca. 1796-1870) in 1817, and they had four sons and two daughters. According to the Annals of Smith of Cantley, Balby, and Doncaster, County York (1878), Thomas devoted much of his leisure time to fine arts, primarily sketching, drawing, lithography, and etching on copper. He collaborated often with his relative Jonathan Richardson, who eventually became a skilled lithographic printer.
Animals in art; Art, Amateur -- Great Britain; Birds in art; Etching -- Great Britain; Quakers -- Great Britain; Ships in art; Botanical illustrations; Children's art; Etchings; Graphite drawings; Pen and ink drawings; Juvenilia; Landscape drawings; Lithographs; Printing plates; Watercolors; Backhouse, Edward, 1808-1879; Backhouse, John Mounsey; Backhouse, Lucy Backhouse, 1812-1872; Backhouse, Rachel, 1826-1898; Backhouse, Thomas J. (Thomas James), 1810-1857; Barclay, Ann Ford, 1822-1913; Barclay, Elizabeth Gurney; Cave, Henry, 1779-1836; Davison, W.; Mounsey, Edward Backhouse, 1840-1911; Mounsey, J. C.; Mounsey, Thomas, 1793-1850; Pease, Susan; Pike, Lydia; Richardson, Jonathan, 1802-ca. 1880; Sparkes, J. M.; Backus family; Mounsey family
- Albums, Series I
  - Album of etchings, drawings, and lithographs by Edward Backhouse and others, 1819-1856; Backhouse, Edward, 1808-1879; 1 v. (76 leaves, with blanks); 36 cm (Box Vol. 1)
    Scope and Contents
    The album includes etchings and lithographs by Edward Backhouse, together with work by other family members, presented "to his dear nephew, Edward Backhouse Mounsey, 1855." This was the year in which he married Katherine Mounsey, and having no children of their own, probably saw young Edward as the son he never had.
    On the following leaf he has written, "Sketches from Nature by Edward Backhouse, mostly taken in 1829." There are 224 separate items including several original watercolors.
    This album gathers together a comprehensive collection of Edward Backhouse's private and public work, much of which is very ephemeral and possibly unrecorded elsewhere. It starts with examples from when he was just 12 years old, and shows him as a gifted watercolor artist, skilful etcher and engraver, and early exponent of lithography.
    Work by Edward Backhouse includes (but is not limited to): several drawings and numerous fine etchings of birds; several drawings and many etchings of varied animals (including tigers, a weasel, warthog (?), stag, lion, elephant, bull, polar bear, rhinoceros, and seals); numerous drawings, etchings, and lithographs of ships of all sorts; landscape etchings and lithographs, including scenery from the Swiss Alps.
    Work by Edward Backhouse Mounsey includes: numerous drawings and etchings of ships and marine scenes; etchings of animals; etchings of landscapes.
    Contributions from other family members are much less frequent. They include work (in varied media) by Lucy Backhouse Backhouse, T.J. Backhouse, A.B. (presumably Ann Ford Barclay), Homasia Bardon, W. Davison, J.C. Mounsey, Thomas Mounsey, Susan Pease, and Jonathan Richardson.
    There are also a number of unsigned works.
    The album includes etchings and lithographs by Edward Backhouse, together with examples from other family members, presented "to his dear nephew, Edward Backhouse Mounsey, 1855." This was the year in which he married Katherine Mounsey, and having no children of their own, probably saw young Edward as the son he never had.
    On the following leaf he has written, "Sketches from Nature by Edward Backhouse, mostly taken in 1829." There are 224 separate items including several original watercolours, and the album also contains work by his nephew Edward, W. Davison, Homasia Bardon, J.C. Mounsey, Susan Pease, Eliz. B.
    This album gathers together a comprehensive collection of his private and public work, much of which is very ephemeral and possibly unrecorded elsewhere. It starts with examples from when he was just 12 years old, and shows him as a gifted watercolour artist, skilful etcher and engraver, and early exponent of lithography.
    Birds in art; Ships in art; Animals in art; Marines (Visual works)
  - Album of etchings, drawings, and lithographs belonging to Rachel Backhouse, of Pilmore Hall, 1831-1848; 1 volume (58 leaves, with many blanks); 29 cm (Box Vol. 2)
    Contains artwork by a great variety of family members. A pencil note by E.B. Mounsey (the younger) on the front endpaper states: "much here belongs to Rachel Backhouse, and came from Pilmore." Rachel was the wife of Alfred Backhouse, of Pilmore Hall, Rockcliffe Park.
    The album comprises 32 items. There is evidence of some leaves being removed, presumably by the family at some point in its history. Some of the items are signed and dated; dates range from 1831 to 1848.
    Items include: two engravings of wild cats by Edward Backhouse; engravings of Dinsdale Baths and Dinsdale Woods & Hotel by J.M. Sparkes; four botanical watercolors, one initialled S.B.; a watercolor of a moth by Lucy Backhouse Backhouse; a sepia drawing of ground squirrels by Ann Ford Barclay; an unsigned tinted lithograph of a castle; a sepia drawing of a knife grinder by Lydia Pike; a fine architectural drawing in graphite, by John Mounsey Backhouse; a graphite drawing of Schladern, Germany, by E.J.B.; a graphite drawing of a goat's head by H.B.; an etching of a peasant with a pipe, by the York artist, H[enry] Cave; an unsigned full-page sepia lithograph of an Arabian battle scene; two woodcuts of a dead duck, and a hawk, by E. Gurney Barclay; a graphite drawing of a lioness and cubs, by E. Gurney Barclay; an unsigned engraving of Netley Abbey by Moonlight; two large colored lithographs of a cat and a dog; a graphite drawing of one of the family houses; and two small portrait engravings.
    Landscape drawings; Botanical illustrations; Animals in art
- Etchings and drawing book by Edward Backhouse Mounsey, Series II
  - Cod fishing, 1855; Mounsey, Edward Backhouse, 1840-1911; 1 etching; 14 x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Four copies.
  - Elephant attacked by a tiger, 1854; Mounsey, Edward Backhouse, 1840-1911; 1 etching; 12 x 17 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Six copies.
  - "Fly fishing, favorable wind, & trout rising as fast as possible", 1854; Mounsey, Edward Backhouse, 1840-1911; 1 etching; 17 x 23 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Comical etching of a fisherman with his line caught in a tree overhead. Animals gather on the opposite riverbank. Six copies.
  - Shipwreck, 1854; Mounsey, Edward Backhouse, 1840-1911; 1 etching; 17 x 23 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    One copy.
  - Lighthouse, 1854; Mounsey, Edward Backhouse, 1840-1911; 1 etching; 22 x 14 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Seven copies.
  - Castle and village, 1855; Mounsey, Edward Backhouse, 1840-1911; 1 etching; 13 x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Five copies.
  - Shipwreck, or naval battle scene, 1855; Mounsey, Edward Backhouse, 1840-1911; 1 etching; 14 x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Jericho, 1855; Mounsey, Edward Backhouse, 1840-1911; 1 etching; 14 x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ships wrecked on ice floes, 1854; Mounsey, Edward Backhouse, 1840-1911; 1 etching; 14 x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - A ship in arctic waters, 1854; Mounsey, Edward Backhouse, 1840-1911; 1 etching; 14 x 21 cm (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - A kayak in arctic waters, 1854; Mounsey, Edward Backhouse, 1840-1911; 1 etching; 10 x 13 cm (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Three copies.
  - A double-masted ship, 1854; Mounsey, Edward Backhouse, 1840-1911; 1 etching; 6 x 10 cm (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - A ship aflame (?) on choppy waters, 1855; Mounsey, Edward Backhouse, 1840-1911; 1 etching; 13 x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - A boat near shore, 1847; Mounsey, Edward Backhouse, 1840-1911; 1 graphite drawing; 18 x 30 cm (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Drawing book, 1852; Mounsey, Edward Backhouse, 1840-1911; 16 leaves of graphite drawings; 18 x 24 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
    The drawing book is inscribed: E.B. Mounsey, 1852. The 14 leaves of drawings mainly depict houses and architectural details, with two drawings of boats. Also loosely inserted is one comic sketch, in graphite, of an elephant (in man's clothing), and another graphite sketch of a ship and whale.
- Copper plates by Thomas Mounsey, Series III
  - Etched copper plate depicting a stately ivy-covered mansion, 1819; Mounsey, Thomas, 1793-1850; 1 printing plate: copper; 12 x 15 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Printing plates
  - Etched copper plate depicting a lake within a hilly landscape, 1822; Mounsey, Thomas, 1793-1850; 1 printing plate: copper; 10 x 16 cm (Box 1, Folder 17)